Guide to the International Monitor Institute. Middle East videotapes, 1991-2008 RL.00606
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Middle East videotapes, circa 1991-2008, 80 boxes
  - B-Roll from "Saddam's Killing Fields"-Roll 5, PAL VHS [TRT: 01:00:00] (Box 331, Video-cassette ME216)
    50-36 Masoud's visit abroad to find money and arms. Highest level of authority.
    Kanan looking at passports of government agents. Audio cassettes of taped, bugged conversations.
    57-39 Housewives chat.
    00-30 Talabani bugged.
    07-00 Security magazines - one on deterioration of morality.
    Files on "active targets... we have a number of interesting, etc. variety of subjects and shots.
    External night time shot of building where documents housed.
    14-25 Index of saboteurs.
    Kanan's reaction: retakes. "I'm tired, the place was real mess... what kind of people were employed in the security." Retake: "What we found in there was a humdrum provincial security office in a dinky little town on the edge of Iraq... Nothing sensational."
    Retake: "I'm tired, the room was a mess... tiny little provincial town on the edges of Iraq. Provincial bureaucrats running.. ."
    Retake: the best.
  - B-Roll from "Saddam's Killing Fields"-Roll 5A, PAL VHS [TRT: 00:30:00] (Box 331, Video-cassette ME217)
  - B-Roll from "Saddam's Killing Fields"-Roll 6, PAL VHS [TRT: 01:00:00] (Box 331, Video-cassette ME218)
    Travelling shots on road to Suleimaniya - 06-01-52-00.
    Shots of driver 06-03-09-20.
    Travelling shots of road etc.
    Dragon mountain 06-05-03-00.
    Kanan inside car 06-21-13-00.
    More travelling shots and car interior with Shalaw.
    Visit to settlement - "concentration camp" - 06-10-40-12.
    Police station - 06-11-11-15 PPI-fr.
    Kanan walks around and general views (gvs.).
    Women walking around with water containers 06-12-17-17.
    Gvs of street.
    Children at school cheer and wave. 06-14-41-22.
    File back into school.
    Seated on floor inside classrooms 06-16-01-24.
    Classes.
    Shalaw: talks about how Kurdish people looted the schools just as the Iraqi troops had in Kuwait - part of the Ba'ath culture - everyone for himself. 06-19-2o-00.
    Gvs. settlement from school roof.
    Water supply 06-20-41-19.
    Women with water buckets on shoulders.
    At the taps.
    Gvs. of landscape near Suleimaniya. 06-22-1.
    Meeting with Teimour at Patriotic Union of Kurdistan (PUK) camp - 06-26-02-19.
    Talks to Kurdish man.
    Walking shot 06-27-40-24; shot from back also.
    Gvs. of camp 06-30-20-13.
    Guards standing at main gate.
    Kanan talks to boy. 06-32-03-00.
    More gvs. Interior (int.) Teimour interview 06-34-21-14.
  - B-Roll from "Saddam's Killing Fields"-Roll 6A, PAL VHS [TRT: 00:30:00] (Box 322, Video-cassette ME219)
  - B-Roll from "Saddam's Killing Fields"-Roll 7, PAL VHS [TRT: 01:00:00] (Box 322, Video-cassette ME220)
    Interview with Taymour at Patriotic Union of Kurdistan (PUK) base.
    PUK officials talk about documents in Suleimaniya.
    Also about "strange behaviour," i.e. sexual perversity, of Ba'ath. Also about anfal... legitimation of destruction of Halabaja 10 months before chemical attack... role of presidential office in issuing death certificate, etc., etc., microcassettes... shots from window. More PUK disclosures.
    Outside security headquarters Suleimaniya/The eye.
    Through main gate, burnt facade. Boys wander in. Kanan walks towards camera.
    The anfal sign at the local post office in Suleimaniya.
    General views (gvs.) of Suleimaniya. Inside building.
    Ba'ath party headquarters now full of refugees. Bullet pocked walls.
    The list of 14,000 people presented by PUK at Kirkuk base.
    Refugees on the way to Askar.
    Pan around Askar.
    Gvs. of countryside, Kurd sits smoking cigarette.(Wind noise). Man prays.
    Travelling shots with vehicles. Two men talking.
    Interview with Shalaw's uncle about attack on Askar with chemical weapons and village survivors becoming Anfal victims.
    Shots of Askar demolished by Iraqis.
  - B-Roll from "Saddam's Killing Fields"-Roll 7A, PAL VHS [TRT: 00:30:00] (Box 322, Video-cassette ME221)
  - B-Roll from "Saddam's Killing Fields"-Roll 8, PAL VHS [TRT: 01:00:00] (Box 322, Video-cassette ME222)
    Teimour walks with Shalaw in Suleimaniya. Forward and backwards.
    2-43 Travelling shot through Suleimaniya from inside car.
    Shalaw: On what happened to Anfal victims. "They didn't to kill these people inside the Kurdish areas."
    Explains how local people came to be buried in Kurdish areas.
    Jahsh's role.
    10-30 Says more than 170,000 executed at border area.
    Talks about heads being severed, including that of mentally sick boy, and sold to government for 10,000 dinar.
    Patriotic Union of Kurdistan (PUK) district branch - man talks about list of Anfal victims.
    Travelling shots towards Chamchamal.
    Refugees at side of road fleeing. "We're afraid of Army. They're bombing Chamchamal. So we left." Women washing. Refugees in back of truck.
    Travelling shots towards Askar. Driver says he hates Jahsh.
    Drive past ruined village - Anfal victims.
    Askar/Goptapa - ruins, graves, Kanan looks at chemical weapons shells vistas of monument with graves of chemical weapons victims.
    Interview with Shalaw. Pans across ruined village.
    Kanan stands out in front of Talabani’s headquarters.
    Interview with Shalaw's relative who tried to save family from chemical weapons with atropine injections (Kurdish).
    Kanan says he doesn't think he's going to be able to get them out. "They're studying them from the point of view of cleaning out their own houses." Says we've been snubbed on succession of occasions... all they know is their private grudges.
    Saladhin cafe.
    Kaman: "After that charade last night, we've been snubbed four times... beginning to think unlikely they will come out... petty political interests over historic things that have been done to the Kurdish people." General views (gvs.) inside tea shop.
  - B-Roll from "Saddam's Killing Fields"-Roll 8A, PAL VHS [TRT: 00:30:00] (Box 322, Video-cassette ME223)
  - B-Roll from "Saddam's Killing Fields"-Roll 9, PAL VHS [TRT: 01:00:00] (Box 322, Video-cassette ME224)
    "Kanan looks at documents with socialist. Diary of military intelligence officer in Arbil. Jan. 17 - on how to rig elections - the importance of not wearing military uniform. (Interference) warning that those who don't participate will be dismissed.
    "Degrees of proclivities - wine, sex, playing cards - "how can he be bought with money."
    Two look at documents on floor. "Agents watching over other agents." Military intelligence file - transcripts of telephone bugs - agents watching other security agents - index. Who talked with who and about what.
    Single figure.
    Kanan - "I get the feeling of routine... no overall sense of what is going on - bureaucracies out of control Kafkaesque... arbitrary...
    Petrol filling station. Our taxi fills up and drives away.
    Guli Ali Beg refugees.
    10-05 General views (gvs.) of mountains at Sheikh Wassan. Pans. Balisan valley. First region to suffer from chemical weapons attack in Kurdistan. Villagers show chemical weapons shell to Kanan. Walk off to mountain side to inspect the damage. Villagers tell us what happened. Dig up further shells on mountainside. "Reminds me of the American war college which said no chemical weapons used in Kurdistan. We're in K and this undoubtedly a chemical weapons shell." Kanan. "German markings on the bomb." Withered trees. Having tea inside house with villagers.
    Kanan led into another pile of documents. Level of penetration. Names of traitors. Pictures of captives. Diary of cultural notebook of Arab Ba'ath. MOD Baghdad box gvs. of bundled files. Windows. Cutaways. Kanan sorting through files (and finding tape of Ali Hassan Majid and his comments on Anfal... plays tape." Close-ups of tape recorder. Hear voice of man in question. Other files - Kurdish mercenaries.
    12-57 Kanan: "I find these piles of paper unbelievably depressing... the amount of pain and violence written on these papers, boxes and boxes of peoples lives extracted under torture built on lies and violence, half of the people here are dead. Do we have the right to ask for these to come out and be exposed?"
    15-07 Arbil - gvs. of dusk street scenes and young girls. Bridal dresses. Shops of young girls buying wedding dresses, cosmetics. Shops.
    Interview with communist party member on experiments on prisons with chemical weapons and bacteriological substances. Man at desk. Communist documents. Kanan enters and looks at docs. Empties sack. Exterior (ext.) shots as well. Goes through what he finds. Executions. students outside Iraq, communists who have escaped. Saboteurs. Political files. Agents armed by security forces. "Armed killers."
  - B-Roll From "Saddam's Killing Fields"-Roll 9A, PAL VHS [TRT: 00:30:00] (Box 322, Video-cassette ME225)
  - B-Roll From "Saddam's Killing Fields"-Roll 10, PAL VHS [TRT: 01:00:00] (Box 322, Video-cassette ME226)
    Guli Ali Beg - Kanan the tourist. Wedding party. Dancing.
    Koshtapa - women with photos, paintings, exterior (ext.), interior (int.) house with bereaved women. Picture shrine. They tell their story.
    Ext. of house plus interview and presence of Barzani Takrit when menfolk were taken away. Crying woman.
    33-36 ptc by Kanan. "Dress-rehearsal for the Anfal campaign." Woman holds up passports of missing Barzani men. Driving through Koshtapa.
    35-46 Dr. Jaafar on rooftop in Arbil talks about the fate of the Sheikh Wassan victims. Silhouette.
    General views (gvs.) of Arbil castle.
    Hospital where these poisoned people from Sheikh Wissan were turned away from. Corridors int. and ext. Prison in Arbil where they were brought before execution.
    52-40 Baharka camp. Few inhabitants now. Plastic sheeting initially given. Pits forced to live in.
    Kanan talks about what happened.
    Kurd explains how his parents fared, etc.
    Second Kurdish man tells about the experience.
    Kanan: "We're not going to come out with any documents.. ."
    Masoud Barzani interview. Walking shots. (Translated?)
    Shots of documents, etc. (Kurdistan Democratic Party [KDP]) Man opens cases and flicks through documents. Cutaways.
    Retake of entry by Kanan, and searching through boxes.
    File of agent in security department recruited at 16. Completely trustworthy.
    Presidential palace wants information about people, many women included.
    Collecting information using Turkish agent for military intelligence - on active targets. Picture of agent concerned.
    Anfal operation as directed by Saddam. Says some saboteur units located in land and document requests their elimination. (1988 Aug.)Saddam - "It is necessary for very active and non-traditional work - implies destruction of houses and chemical weapons attacks."
  - B-Roll from "Saddam's Killing Fields"-Roll 10A, PAL VHS [TRT: 00:30:00] (Box 331, Video-cassette ME227)
  - B-Roll from "Saddam's Killing Fields"-Roll 10/10A, PAL VHS [TRT: 2:00:00] (Box 322, Video-cassette ME228)
  - B-Roll from "Saddam's Killing Fields"-Roll 11, PAL VHS [TRT: 01:00:00] (Box 322, Video-cassette ME229)
    Kanan still searches files - individuals. Some documents burnt. Running of agents. "Everything handwritten like Babylonian scribes of thousands of years ago." Register of high-ranking agents in Arbil. "All these are people who have sold their souls in one way or another." Sits at desk.
    Letter from Arbil director of security - Ali Hassan al-Majid liquidation of Communist Party cadre whose body has been burnt.
    Interview with Communist Party archivist on Ba'ath eavesdropping and filming women undressing.
    13-37 Arbil college for girls classroom shots.
    Girls file through main school corridor.
    Girls in main hall - seated.
    Interview with Arbil police director. Aid snaps to attention on entering and leaving room. Two shot of Kanan and director.
    Director walks self-consciously through corridor.
    Host of general filing, archiving, typing shots from police building, etc. etc.
    Halabja postcards for sale.
    Travelling by bus. Shots of Kanan looking pensive. Driving to Talabani's headquarters.
    Patriotic Union of Kurdistan (PUK) training sequences.
  - B-Roll from "Saddam's Killing Fields"-Roll 11A, PAL VHS [TRT: 00:30:00] (Box 322, Video-cassette ME230)
  - B-Roll from "Saddam's Killing Fields"-Roll 12, PAL VHS [TRT: 00:60:00] (Box 331, Video-cassette ME231)
    "Bus arrives at Patriotic Union of Kurdistan (PUK) camp. Kan waits at main gate. General views (gvs.) of camp and mountains around. Fort.
    Grave yard - mainly victims of Intifada. Three women at grave. Gvs.
    Kanan - "short term considerations... blame them all for... basest of reasons."
    8-15 Chamchamal - Suresh. Gvs. of streets. Kurdistan Democratic Party (KDP) camp.
    Iraqi Army frontline. Tank on horizon. Guerrillas hang around frontline areas. RPG 7 rockets on back of one.
    Woman collects water.
    Anfal victims surround us and show fingers to demonstrate how many family members lost. Riot develops.
    Boys run ahead of landcruiser in Suresh.
    Interview with man and woman about experiences of Anfal. Woman talks of girls being raped.
    Fort where Anfal carriages are discovered. Victims have disappeared. Peshmerga holds up clothes.
    Variety of shots - pans, etc. Kanan taking photos. Peshmerga with children's clothes.
    Tank dug-outs. Iranian position in distance. Children's garments.
    Peshmerga commander talks.
    Kanan ptc.
    KPTC, silence and shame.
    Walking around interior of fort - Anfal victims' excrement. Shots of carriages atop fort. Travelling shots of fort. General travelling shots. Several more carriages. Cross-country shots from vehicle. Refugees in lorry Derbend Dikhan. General shots - very beautiful.
  - B-Roll from "Saddam's Killing Fields"-Roll 12A, PAL VHS [TRT: 00:30:00] (Box 331, Video-cassette ME232)
  - B-Roll from "Saddam's Killing Fields"-Roll 13, PAL VHS [TRT: 01:00:00] (Box 331, Video-cassette ME233)
    Suleimaniya - Kanan goes walk-about in security headquarters. He reads from document picked up from floor. "Those that have had their freedom stolen from them look forward to the day when Arab history will return to its brilliance."
    Letter to security unit - on mother of "criminal karim."
    K walks into torture cells in basement.
    Woman's prison. Poems on wall.
    The cells of "no return."
    Religious "relics." "The only time I have seen this is the shrines.
    KPTC confessions.
    Very dim exterior shot of security headquarters.
    Tracking shot along streets at night.
    Nighttime time shots of shops, restaurants, etc.
    Kanan, in car: "Families asking for videos not to be sold.
    N.B. rape.
    Hunt for videos in Suleimaniya.
    TV shots of Suleimaniya during Intifada - dead bodies of security agents.
    Video parlour - watching Western thriller.
    Then torture video.
    Various ptc from Kanan.
    Videos - filmed off screen - execution. Shiites in south.
    Travelling shots - crossing river with ferry.
    Gr on camera on ferry.
    Travelling shots from car.
    Car in shot.
    Accra - various - town that close to government and survived relatively unscarred.
    Long shot of car on road to Zakho.
    Travelling shots.
    TV - man singing who Anfaled.
  - B-Roll From "Saddam's Killing Fields"-Roll 13A, PAL VHS [00:30:00] (Box 331, Video-cassette ME234)
  - K Archive (1), PAL Hi-8 [TRT:1:02:00] (2 copies) (Box 310 and 331, Video-cassette ME235)
    Original Credits: Tape obtained by Gwynne Roberts on his last trip to Kurdistan which was funded in part by IMI.
    Original tape is labeled as follows:
    Kurdistan Democratic Party (KDP)/explosives, arrests.
    2 executions and 2 more torture victims.
  - K Archives (2), PAL Hi-8 [TRT:1:01:00] (2 copies) (Box 309 and 322, Video-cassette ME236)
    (1) Chemical weapons, gas attack on Sheik Weissen (?) village, 1987 Apr.
    (2) Barzan Anfal shot by Iraqis, 1987 Apr.
  - K Archives (3), PAL Hi-8 [TRT:0:15:00] (2 copies) (Box 309 and 330, Video-cassette ME237)
    Original tape labeled as follows:
    Barzan Anfal (continued).
  - Bombardment chimique des kurdes d'Irak/ - Débat sur les armes chimiques, SECAM VHS [TRT:2:30:00] (Box 330, Video-cassette ME238)
    Paris Kurdish Institute Tape #3
  - Le Kurdistan liberé: Un an après la Guerre du Golfe, Entre l'Espoir et le Doute, SECAM VHS [TRT:0:12:29] (2 copies) (Box 309 and 330, Video-cassette ME239)
    Language: French/Kurdish
    Producer: France Libertés - Fondation Danielle Mitterand
    Paris Kurdish Institute Tape #6
    Dated 1992 May
    Short collection of images made by the French relief organization France Libertés that documents the situation in Kurdistan after the Gulf War and in particular the elections that occurred that year. Short film jumps around with quick cuts of scenes of night time rockets being fired and woman and children rejoicing at Kurdish Independence, also includes people celebrating in the streets, as well as Jalal Talabani and the Syrian border crossing. One shot lists Sayyid Sadiq, une école dans les ruines, the work of the Foundation Danielle Mitterand building schools for the Kurds.
    At 00:11:31 shot of Françoise Brie from France Libertés.
  - Réfugiés kurdes de Bourg-Lastic, SECAM VHS [TRT:0:11:38] (Box 330, Video-cassette ME240)
    Paris Kurdish Institute Tape #11
    Réfugiés. Interview avec les enfants kurdes.
    Refugees, interviews with Kurdish children.
  - I Curdi e il Kurdistan, SECAM VHS [TRT:0:38:43] (Box 330, Video-cassette ME241)
    Language: Italian
    Paris Kurdish Institute Tape #12
    Italian documentary on the Kurds and Kurdistan, the exodus, accord de 1975, Halabaja. Interview avec K. Nezan.
  - Kurdes: Les oubliés de l'histoire, SECAM VHS [TRT:0:59:23] (Box 309: 2 copies, 2 originals) (Box 309, Video-cassette ME242)
    Producer: Antenne 2
    Paris Kurdish Institute Tape #27
    French television program hosted by Daniel Bilalian about the Kurds; includes a discussion with various French journalists, activists and politicians about the Kurdish issue, including Kendal Nezan, Director of the Paris Kurdish Institute, Mahmoud Osman from the Kurdish Socialist Party, and Dr. Frederic Tissot, who has been involved with Kurdish issues in France, as well as an interview with Hamed Youssef Hamadi, Iraqi Minister of Information, and Henry Kissinger. Also interviewed are French politicians including, Jean-François Deniau, deputy of the French Democratic Union party, as well as a report from a special envoy in Turkey named Jerome Bony; also includes interviews with Kurdish refugees in French. The program includes footage of the exodus of 1991, as well as peshmerga fighting the guerilla war against Iraq. The subject of the program is what to do about the situation of the Kurds after the suppression of the intifada by the Iraqi regime.
    Exode de 1991. Débat.
  - Voyage au pays kurde, SECAM VHS [TRT: 01:00:00] (original) (Box 321, Video-cassette ME243)
    Paris Kurdish Institute Tape #31
    Dated 1982
    Historical footage of the Kurds, daily life, etc., includes an interview at the end with unknown person.
    Interview. Vie quotidienne. Vie nomade. Elevage. Agriculture.
    Pierre Foque.
  - Reportages sur l'éxode kurde et la révolte des chiites, SECAM VHS [TRT:0:54:00] (2 copies) (Box 309 and 330, Video-cassette ME244)
    Language: English/German
    Producer: CNN, RTL et ZDF
    Paris Kurdish Institute Tape #34
    Very Poor Quality.
    Tape is a collection of American and German news reports on the Kurdish exodus refugee crisis following the end of the Gulf War and the uprisings in 1991. CNN and German network news document the refugee crisis and report on the Kurdish plight. Includes some reports on refugee camps in Saudi Arabia and in Kuwait near Safwar, and on the humanitarian suffering of the Kurds.
  - Kurdistan iranien, SECAM VHS [TRT:0:29:58] (Box 330, Video-cassette ME245)
    Producer: Aide Médicale International
    Original Credits: Directors, writers: F. Veber/F. Tissot
    Paris Kurdish Institute Tape #46
    Résistence armée. Democratic Party of Iranian Kurdistan (PDK Iran). Vie quotidienne.
  - Irak sous le régime de Saddam Hussein, SECAM VHS [TRT:0:40:00] (Box 330, Video-cassette ME246)
    Paris Kurdish Institute Tape #51
    French version of Charles Glass documentary on the regime of Saddam Hussein, see also ME109, Tape B for English version.
  - Curdi: morte annunciata di un popolo, SECAM VHS [TRT:0:09:00] (3 copies) (Box 309 and 350, Video-cassette ME247)
    Producer: Insiem per la Pace
    Paris Kurdish Institute Tape #56
    Images from the Kurdish Exodus of 1991.
  - La révolte des kurdes, SECAM VHS [TRT: 01:30:00] (2 copies) (Box 309 and 350, Video-cassette ME248)
    Producer: Jean Bertolino
    Paris Kurdish Institute Tape #60
    Interview avec M. Ghassemlou. Révolte du Kurdistan d'Irak de 1961. Révolte du Kurdistan d'Iran.
  - Offensive iranienne contre le QG. du PDK-Iran et l'Hopital A.M.I., SECAM VHS [TRT:0:17:00] (2 copies) (Box 309 and 350, Video-cassette ME249)
    Paris Kurdish Institute Tape #61
    Dated 1993 Mar. 13.
    Guerre. Bombardements.
  - We Are Not Animals, SECAM VHS [TRT: 00:30:00] (2 copies) (Box 309 and 350, Video-cassette ME250)
    Producer: Institut Kurde
    Paris Kurdish Institute Tape #77
    Exode. Interviews avec Barzani et Talabani. Concert de Živan au Kurdistan.
  - The Voice of Kurdistan, SECAM VHS [TRT:1:02:00] (2 copies) (Box 311 and 350, Video-cassette ME251)
    Producer: Kurdistan Film Collective. A 407 Films Production
    Original Credits: Journalist's account: Gwynne Roberts. Co-directed (for part on Patriotic Union of Kurdistan [PUK]): Johannes Melbinger, Peter Stalleger. Directed by Jacqueline Bottagisio and Georges Drion. Produced by Georges Drion
    Paris Kurdish Institute Tape #78
    Dated 1980